Finding Aid for Personnel Office (University of Michigan) Records, 1940-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Personnel Office (University of Michigan) records
1940-1999
1958-1995
University of Michigan. Personnel Office.
8757 Bimu B28 2
Compensation and Staff Relations division of the Personnel Office of the University of Michigan. Administrative records documenting personnel policies and procedures, records detailing negotiation and administration of the University's contract with the Graduate Employees Organization; memoranda to deans, directors and department heads; also records documenting the activities of numerous employees' unions at the university.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
38.5 linear feet
Records were transferred from the Personnel Office (Donor No. 7384 ) in various accessions
The Personnel Office records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Personnel Office record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 31
Patient/Client Records -- Boxes 31
The University of Michigan Personnel Office was established on January 26, 1945. The office formally reports to the Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs. Among the Personnel Office's many responsibilities are the development and implementation of the university's personnel policies, administration of the faculty promotion and tenure granting process, and negotiation and administration of contracts with unionized university employees. It also maintains the official employment record for all faculty and staff. In compliance with the Michigan Freedom of Information Act, the Personnel Office makes salary information for all university employees available to the public (The annually published salary list is located in the University of Michigan Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action publications record group).
The Personnel Office develops and implements personnel policies for the University of Michigan. The office establishes the guidelines that govern the hiring and firing of all university staff, including academic faculty. The salary grades which determine an employee's initial compensation are based on the skills necessary to fill a position as well as previous experience relating to that position.
Recommendations for faculty promotions and granting of tenure are initiated by the department, college or school. These recommendations are transmitted through the Personnel Office to the president and provost and executive vice president for academic affairs, and then to the Board of Regents for final action.
The Personnel Office is the university's agent in labor negotiations with various staff and professional bargaining units. In the late 1950s, the University adopted a policy of neutrality with regards to employee union activities. Employees were allowed to seek union representation in grievance and other procedures. However, the university still refused to recognize any one union to speak for all employees, and thus refused to bargain collectively. At this time, the university saw an upswing in union activity, with the Association of Federal, State, and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), Local 1583, at the forefront. The Building Service Employees' International Union (BSEIU), Local 378, was also active on campus at this time.
In 1965, another surge in activity took place following the state's revision of the Hutchinson Act, recognizing the right of government employees to bargain collectively. In 1968, the Michigan Labor Mediation Board recognized the University's service and maintenance employees as an appropriate collective bargaining unit. These employees soon elected AFSCME to represent them. The first union contract signed by the university became effective September 13, 1968. The complexities of these negotiations can be seen in the events of 1970 when graduate student assistants petitioned the Michigan Employment Relations Commission (MERC) for recognition of a collective bargaining unit. The university argued that if graduate students were to be considered employees, they did not compose a bargaining unit by themselves, but rather were a component part of several larger bargaining units. Without ruling on the employment issue, MERC dismissed the student petition based on the university's second argument.
In February 1994, the Personnel Office and the Affirmative Action Office were combined into a new entity, Human Resources and Affirmative Action (HRAA).
The Personnel Office records comprise 31 linear feet and span a wide range of years from the 1940s to the early 1990s. The records document the activities of the office prior to its 1994 consolidation with the Affirmative Action Office. The office is now part of Human Resources and Affirmative Action. The records have been filed as received from the unit in periodic accessions. As such there is considerable overlap in topics covered and dates of coverage within the various records series. Files relating to specific promotion and tenure cases are in a separate record group, University of Michigan Office of Human Resources and Affirmative Action Promotion Casebooks. A finding aid for these records is available in the Bentley Library.
The records of the Personnel Office are divided into nine series: Topical Files of Assistant to the Vice President for Academic Affairs: Charles Allmand; Topical Files of Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs-Personnel Administration: Colleen Dolan-Greene; Personnel Data Systems (PDS) Files; Graduate Student Assistants (GSA)/Graduate Employees Organization (GEO) Files; Memoranda to Deans, Directors, and Department Heads; Administrative Files, 1980-1992; Administrative Files, 1970-1994; Labor Relations, and Administrative Files, 1963-1994.
Subjects:
Graduate Employees Organization (University of Michigan); Labor--Michigan.; Universities and colleges--Employees--Labor unions--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Employees.Employees.; University of Michigan--Finance.Finance.; University of Michigan. Personnel Office.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.; Strikes and lockouts--Michigan.; AFSCME. Local 1583 (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
- Topical Files of Assistant to the Vice President for Academic Affairs
  The Topical Files series originate from the offices of Assistant to the Vice President for Academic Affairs. In 1986 the title of the office was changed from Assistant to the Vice President for Academic Affairs to Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs-Personnel Administration, although responsibilities remained the same. The series is divided into two subseries reflecting the tenure of the two individuals who held the office: Charles Allmand, 1969-1985 and Colleen Dolan Greene, 1986-1993. Both subseries reflect the wide ranging responsibilities of the Personnel Office within the University of Michigan infrastructure.
  - Charles All, 1961-1985
    - 1969-1985
      The Topical Files of Assistant to the Vice President for Academic Affairs of Charles Allmand, 1969-1985 (8.5 linear ft.) includes information on the many university divisions with personnel concerns, and information on numerous faculty and staff issues including appointment, promotion and tenure procedures.
      - Academic Calendar, 1969-1978 (Box 1)
      - Academic Freedom, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
      - Academic Planning and Analysis Office, 1974-1981 (Box 1)
      - Administrative Cost Study, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
      - Administrators, Academic, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
      - Affirmative Action Availability and Utilization, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
      - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1968-1976 (Box 1)
      - American Council on Education (ACE), 1965-1979 (Box 1)
      - Anniversary Review / Salary Increases, 1966-1977 (Box 1)
      - Appeal Procedures
        - General, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
        - Students, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
      - Appointment and Promotion Procedures
        - General, 1962-1975 (Box 1)
        - Criteria for Faculty, 1970 (Box 1)
        - Instructional Staff, 1974-1980 (Box 1)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
        - Primary and Research Staff, 1980 (Box 1)
        - Tenure, 1974-1975 (Box 31)
      - Appointments
        - Chronological History of 2/9-3/9 Summer Appointments
          - 1975 (Box 1)
          - 1978 (Box 1)
        - Dual Appointments, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
        - Policies, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
        - Summer Appointment Policies, 1963-1977 (Box 1)
      - Architecture and Urban Planning, College of (faculty appointment), 1975 (Box 31)
      - Athletics, Department of
        - General, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
        - Women's Track Team, Discrimination, 1979 (Box 1)
      - Awards, 1965-1979 (Box 2)
      - Budget
        - General, 1973-1979; 6 folders (Box 2)
        - Faculty Salaries, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
        - Program Budget Evaluation System (PBES) for Higher Education, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
        - Projections, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
        - Salaries, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
        - Salary Summaries (Executives, Deans and Directors), 1968-1981 (Box 2)
      - Bureau of School Services, 1966-1972 (Box 2)
      - Business Administration, School of, 1966-1968 (Box 2)
      - Center for Continuing Education of Women (CEW), 1972-1980 (Box 2)
      - Certificate Programs, Nurse Anesthetist, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
      - Civil Liberties Board, 1968-1977 (Box 2)
      - Civil Rights Laws (General Counsel correspondence), 1977 (Box 2)
      - Classification
        - General, 1972-1979 (Box 2)
        - Instructional and Research Staff
          - General, 1965-1978 (Box 2)
          - Faculty Appointments, 1967-1978 (Box 2)
      - Clinical Staff, 1963-1977 (Box 2)
      - Compensation
        - General, 1973-1980 (Box 2)
        - Overseas Staff, 1964-1973 (Box 2)
        - Review, Medical Services Plan, 1978 (Box 2)
      - Conflict of Interest
        - Committee, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
        - Policies, 1965-1978 (Box 2)
      - Copyright, Patent Policies
        - General, 1968-1979 (Box 2)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2)
      - Curators, 1972-1975 (Box 2)
      - Data Systems Center (DSC), 1971-1974 (Box 3)
      - Dean (re: merger of Office of Rackham School of Graduate Studies Dean and Office of Vice President for Research), 1983 (Box 3)
      - Dean Search Committee Procedures, 1977-1983 (Box 3)
      - Deans' Salaries, 1976-1984 (Box 3)
      - Dearborn Campus
        - General
          - 1971-1979 (Box 3)
          - 1980-1984 (Box 3)
        - Faculty Appointments, 1980-1985 (Box 31)
        - Fraud, 1979 (Box 31)
      - Dentistry, School of
        - General, 1969-1987 (Box 3)
      - Education, School of, 1969-1980 (Box 3)
      - Education, Speech and Hearing Sciences Section (Box 3)
      - General, 1972-1980
        - Faculty Appointments, 1977-1980 (Box 31)
      - Educational Assistants, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
      - Emeritus Faculty, 1957-1976 (Box 3)
      - Employment Services Office
        - General, 1975-1979 (Box 3)
        - Fraud, 1976 (Box 31)
      - Engineering, School of
        - General
          - 1966-1980 (Box 3)
          - 1981-1984 (Box 3)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
      - English Language Institute, 1963-1971 (Box 3)
      - Faculty, Definition of (Box 3)
      - Faculty Analysis Project, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
      - Faculty Development Fund, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
      - Faculty Exchange Program
        - General, 1975 (Box 3)
        - Faculty Applications, 1975-1979 (Box 3)
      - Faculty Grievance Procedures, 1972-1984 (Box 3)
      - Faculty Handbook
        - Draft, 1969 (Box 3)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1976 (Box 3)
        - Policies, 1974-1978 (Box 3)
      - Faculty Orientation Program, 1976-1980 (Box 3)
      - Faculty Rights and Responsibilities (Box 3)
      - Fair Labor Standards Act, 1972-1977 (Box 3)
      - Fellows, Michigan Society of
        - General, 1974-1979 (Box 3)
        - Appointment, 1978 (Box 3)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1974-1978 (Box 3)
      - File Review (Study of Women's Salaries)
        - General, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
        - Faculty/Staff Appointment, 1974 (Box 31)
        - No Changes Recommended (Box 3)
        - Non-Teaching Staff (Box 3)
        - Teaching Staff (Box 3)
      - Financial Aid, Office of, 1975-1976 (Box 3)
      - Fiscal Year Change, 1975-1976; 1981 (Box 3)
      - Flint Campus
        - General, 1975-1980 (Box 4)
        - Faculty Appointment, 1978-1979 (Box 31)
      - Form Revisions
        - Form B, 1967 (Box 4)
        - Form E/X, 1971-1983 (Box 4)
        - Form G/G-2, 1960-1979; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Form K (Box 4)
      - Four-day Work Week
        - 1972-1975 (Box 4)
        - 1976-1978 (Box 4)
      - Freedom of Speech, 1977 (Box 4)
      - General Counsel, Office of, 1972-1978 (Box 4)
      - Governmental Services, 1974-1976 (Box 4)
      - Graduate Studies, Horace H. Rackham School of, 1974-1979 (Box 4)
      - Grievances
        - Policies, 1979 (Box 4)
        - Grievance Statistics, 1976-1979 (Box 31)
      - Health Maintenance Organization (HMO), 1974-1979 (Box 4)
      - Hiring Freeze, 1980-1982 (Box 4)
      - Historical Data Committee, Retention of, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Homosexuals, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Honorary Degree Policy, 1980 (Box 4)
      - Hospital, V.A. and Wayne County, 1965-1983 (Box 4)
      - House Bills, (State of Michigan), 1964-1980 (Box 4)
      - Howard Hughes Medical Institute, 1984-1986 (Box 4)
      - Human Growth and Development, Center for (CHGD), 1967-1974; 1981-1982 (Box 4)
      - Industrial Technology Institute (ITI)
        - General, 1981-1984 (Box 4)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1984 (Box 4)
        - Information, Release of, 1969-1979 (Box 4)
      - Institute for Labor and Industrial Relations (ILIR)
        - General, 1967-1981 (Box 4)
        - Tenure, 1975-1981 (Box 31)
      - Institute for the Study of Mental Retardation and Related Disabilities (ISMRRD)
        - General, 1976-1980 (Box 4)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
      - Institutional Cooperation, Committee on (CIC), 1977-1979 (Box 4)
      - Instructional Staff
        - Clinical
          - General, 1975-1985; 2 folders (Box 4)
          - General Counsel Correspondence, 1985 (Box 4)
        - Supplemental, 1975-1984 (Box 4)
      - Intergovernment Personnel Act (IPA) (Box 4)
      - Internal Audit, Office of (UM), 1972-1975 (Box 4)
      - Internal Revenue Service (IRS), 1977-1980 (Box 4)
      - International Center
        - General, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
        - Faculty/Staff Appointments, 1971-1972 (Box 31)
      - Lab for Applied Physics, 1982 (Box 4)
      - Labor Department (State of Michigan), 1972 (Box 4)
      - Law School
        - General, 1971-1979; 1982-1985 (Box 4)
        - Promotion, 1975-1983 (Box 31)
      - Leaves of Absence
        - General, 1969-1984 (Box 4)
        - Reasons, 1976-1978 (Box 31)
      - Lecturers, 1966-1986 (Box 5)
      - Legislation, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
      - Librarians, 1968-1985; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Library Compensation Manual, 1973 (Box 5)
      - Library Evaluation Committee (Box 5)
      - Literature, Science and the Arts, College of, 1975-1985 (Box 5)
      - Los Alamos Laboratory, 1974-1981 (Box 5)
      - Management Information System (MIS) Code Committee (Box 5)
      - Medical Center Reorganization, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
      - Medical School
        - General, 1972-1985; 3 folders (Box 5)
        - Technology Program, 1984 (Box 5)
      - Medical Services Plan
        - General, 1974-1979 (Box 5)
        - Faculty/Staff Appointment, 1975-1978 (Box 31)
      - Memberships, Professional, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
      - Mental Health Research Institute (MHRI), 1981-1983 (Box 5)
      - Moving Expenses, 1966-1978 (Box 5)
      - Music, School of
        - General, 1972-1979 (Box 5)
        - Faculty/Staff Appointment, 1970-1983 (Box 31)
      - Nepotism, 1971-1979 (Box 5)
      - Non-reappointment, Notice of, 1969-1978 (Box 5)
      - Nursing, School of
        - General, 1973-1979 (Box 5)
        - Faculty Appointment, 1977-1979 (Box 31)
      - Occupational Deferment, 1966-1968 (Box 5)
      - Occupational Safety and Environmental Health, Department of (OSEH), 1972-1975 (Box 5)
      - Open Meetings Act, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
      - Orientation
        - Deans/Directors, 1976-1978 (Box 5)
        - Department Chairs, 1978 (Box 5)
        - Instructional Staff, 1978 (Box 5)
      - Outside Employment, 1954-1959; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Professional/Administrative Steering Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
      - Pay Policy, 1973-1979 (Box 6)
      - Payroll Deductions, 1968-1979 (Box 6)
      - Personnel Office
        - General, 1972-1979; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Medical Center, 1977-1979; 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous Policies, 1962-1971 (Box 6)
        - Office of Professional and Administrative Staff Services (OPASS)
          - General, 1970-1983; 2 folders (Box 6)
          - Staff Appointment, 1975-1978 (Box 31)
        - Operational Review, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
        - Reorganization, 1979-1980; 4 folders (Box 6)
        - Reports, 1977-1979 (Box 6)
        - Staff and Union Relations
          - General, 1971-1975 (Box 6)
          - Complaint, 1973 (Box 31)
      - Pharmacy, College of, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
      - Physical Education, Department of, 1974-1978 (Box 6)
      - Policy Coordinator Classification, 1974-1976 (Box 6)
      - Population Planning (School of Public Health) (bulk 1976), 1965-1976 (Box 6)
      - Post-Doctoral Scholars, 1970-1979 (Box 6)
      - President's Annual Report, 1973-1979 (Box 6)
      - Primary Researchers, 1973-1981 (Box 7)
      - Program Discontinuance, Academic, 1976-1979 (Box 7)
      - Promotional Openings Program (POP), 1972-1978 (Box 7)
      - Promotional Statistics
        - 1966-1976 (Box 7)
        - 1976-1977
          - General (Box 7)
          - Faculty Promotion (Box 31)
        - 1977-1978
          - General (Box 31)
          - Faculty Promotion (Box 31)
        - 1978-1979
          - General (Box 7)
          - Faculty Promotion (Box 31)
        - 1979-1980
          - General (Box 7)
          - Faculty Promotion (Box 31)
      - Recruitment, 1962-1978 (Box 7)
      - Reduction in Force (RIF)
        - General, 1971-1978 (Box 7)
        - Staff Appointment, 1973-1975 (Box 31)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2095 ]
      - Regents, 1975-1979 (Box 7)
      - Religion, Report of the Commission on, 1964; 1973-1974 (Box 7)
      - Researchers' Salaries, 1971-1977 (Box 7)
      - Retirement, 1957-1979 (Box 7)
      - Sabbaticals, 1975-1979 (Box 7)
      - Salary Policy, 1959-1976 (Box 7)
      - School/College Administrators Group, 1969-1977 (Box 7)
      - Senate Advisory Committee on University Affairs (SACUA), 1977-1978 (Box 7)
      - Senate Advisory Review Committee (SARC)
        - General, 1969-1977 (Box 7)
        - Complaint, 1976 (Box 31)
        - General Counsel Correspondence, 1977 (Box 31)
          [CR RESTRICTED until July 1 2077 ]
      - Sick Leave
        - General, 1962-1980 (Box 7)
        - Appointment, 1979 (Box 31)
      - Social Research, Institute for (ISR), 1957-1978 (Box 7)
      - Social Security, 1968-1978 (Box 7)
      - Standard Practice Guide (SPG), 1971-1979 (Box 7)
      - Strike and Boycott, 1969-1975 (Box 7)
      - Students, Foreign (immigration status), 1983 (Box 7)
      - Student/Faculty Policy Cluster
        - General, 1984 (Box 7)
        - Faculty Promotion, 1984 (Box 31)
      - Systems and Procedures, Academic Reporting System, 1974 (Box 7)
      - Temporary Employment, 1970-1979 (Box 7)
      - Tenure
        - 1969-1975 (Box 7)
        - General
          - Faculty Promotion (Box 7)
          - General Counsel Correspondence (Box 7)
        - 1976-1980
          - General (Box 7)
          - Faculty Promotion (Box 31)
          - General Counsel Correspondence (Box 7)
      - Tenure Guideline Review (for AAAC), 1977 (Box 7)
      - Training and Development Office, 1970-1979 (Box 8)
      - Tuition Refund Plan, 1969-1978 (Box 8)
      - Unions, 1972-1977 (Box 8)
      - Vice President for Academic Affairs, Office of
        - General, 1962-1979 (Box 8)
        - Faculty Appointment, 1974-1981 (Box 31)
    - 1961-1985
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Postdoctoral Scholars, 1983 (Box 37)
      - College of Pharmacy, 1984-1985 (Box 37)
      - Faculty and Staff Records/Historical Files, 1982-1985 (Box 37)
      - Michigan Research Corporation, 1982-1986 (Box 37)
      - Personnel President's Archival Report, circa 1961-1985; 2 folders (Box 37)
      - Postdoctoral Scholars, 1980-1985; 2 folders (Box 37)
      - Primary Research Staff, 1983-1985 (Box 37)
      - Probationary Period, 1985-1986 (Box 37)
      - Professorships
        - Distinguished University Professorships, 1964-1983 (Box 37)
        - Endowed, 1985 (Box 37)
        - Endowed Chairs Summary, 1973-1986 (Box 37)
        - Named Professorships, 1976-1985 (Box 37)
      - School of Music, 1981-1984 (Box 37)
      - School of Natural Resources, 1983-1985 (Box 37)
      - School of Nursing, 1980-1985 (Box 38)
      - School of Nursing Salary Equity Study, 1985 (Box 38)
      - University Committee on Computer Policy, 1980-1984; 4 folders (Box 38)
      - University Stores System Proposal, 1980-1983; 2 folders (Box 38)
      - Willow Run Labs, 1970-1977 (Box 38)
  - Colleen Dolan-Greene, 1986-1993
    The Topical Files of Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs-Personnel Administration: Colleen Dolan-Greene, 1986-1993 series (5 linear ft.) contains an alphabetical run of administrative files that originated from the office of Dolan-Greene, Charles M. Allmand's successor. The series contains several folders of monthly personnel reports and data comparisons. The series also contains information detailing negotiations with unions representing university employees, tenure and promotion process, and employee salary issues.
    - Academic Affairs, Office of, Review, 1982-1986 (Box 8)
    - Administrative Systems, Office of (OAS), Planning, 1982-1986 (Box 8)
    - Affiliations, Agreements and Contracts, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Affirmative Action Office
      - General, 1986-1988 (Box 8)
      - Quarterly Goal Reports, 1985
        - Salary Analysis, 1979-1986 (Box 8)
        - General, 1979-1986 (Box 8)
        - Faculty and Staff Evaluations, undated (Box 31)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2016 ]
    - Afroamerican and African Studies, Center for (CAAS), 1970-1988 (Box 8)
    - Alternative Work Week Schedules, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Automation and Computing, 1981-1984; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Budget, 1980-1988; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Budget Planning Committee for Salary and Benefits, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Comparative Instructional Salary Data, 1985-1986 (Box 8)
    - Costs, Administrative, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Cross-cultural Communication, 1986-1989 (Box 8)
    - Discipline Guides, 1982-1984 (Box 8)
    - Diversity, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Electronic Calendaring for Grievances Project, 1986 (Box 8)
    - Evaluation of Personnel Office, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Faculty and Staff Transfers and Termination, 1978-1987 (Box 31)
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2017 ]
    - Faculty Merit Increase Program (Box 9)
      - General, 1980-1990; 11 folders (Box 9)
      - Memorandum, 1979-1984 (Box 9)
    - Graduate Student Assistants (GSAs) and Taxation Issue, 1984-1988; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Michigan Mandate, 1988-1990 (Box 9)